Guide to the Richard Berkowitz Papers MSS.421
Fales Library and Special Collections
Richard Berkowitz Papers
1925, 1944-2022, undated
1982-2015
Fales Library and Special Collections
Berkowitz, Richard, 1955-
MSS.421
22.7 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons, 7 flat boxes, and 1 half manuscript box.
47 film reels
1 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
131 audiocassettes
24 videocassettes
2 DVDs
3.02 Gigabytes in 18,824 computer files.
1 websites in 1 archived website.
Richard Berkowitz (b. 1955) is a gay American author, AIDS activist, and a former sex worker. In 1983, Berkowitz and Michael Callen wrote the first safe sex guide, How to Have Sex in an Epidemic: One Approach. Berkowitz continued to write about and advocate for safe sex through the 1980s into the 2000s. The Richard Berkowitz Papers date from 1944 to 2015, with the bulk being between 1982-2015, and document his work as a writer, AIDS activist, and sex worker, as well as his family, his education, his medical history, and Daryl Wein's documentary about Berkowitz's life, Sex Positive. The papers contain correspondence, manuscripts, published material, clippings, programs, photographs, a scrapbook, audiovisual material, and a website.
Conditions Governing Access
Donor permission is required for access. Please contact NYU Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from Richard Berkowitz in 2014. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2014.421, 2015.421.001, 2015.421.002, 2015.421.003, 2015.421.004, and 2016.007.
https://richardberkowitz.com/ was selected by curators and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. There is no accession number associated with the archived website.
Arrangement
The Richard Berkowitz Papers are arranged in eight series, three of which have been further arranged into subseries. The series and subseries in the collection are as follows:
Series I. Correspondence, 1973-2016, undated
Subseries I.A. General, 1973-2016, undated
Subseries I.B. Southern REACH (Regional Expansion of Access and Capacity to Address HIV/AIDS)/Gulf Coast HIV/AIDS Evaluations, 2009-2012
Subseries I.C. Michael Callen Projects, 2012-2015
Subseries I.D. Joseph Sonnabend, 2008-2015
Series II. Education, 1974-1980, undated
Subseries II.A. Rutgers University, 1974-1977, undated
Subseries II.B. New York University, 1977-1980, undated
Series III. Family records, 1925, 1944-1994, undated
Series IV. Financial Records, 1982-2012, undated
Series V. Medical Records, 1979-2002, undated
Series VI. Sex Positive, 2007-2015
Series VII. Sex Work, 1978-2002, undated
Series VIII. Work Files, 1976-2015, undated
Subseries VIII.A. Audio Recordings, 1982-2005, undated
Subseries VIII.B. Correspondence, 1984-2015, undated
Subseries VIII.C. Research Files, 1976-2012, undated
Subseries VIII.D. Writings, 1982-2009
Subseries VIII.E. Archived Website, 2016
Biographical Note
Richard Berkowitz (b. 1955) is a gay American author, AIDS activist, and former sex worker. He graduated from Rutgers University with a degree in communications in 1977. While at Rutgers, he wrote for the campus newspaper, The Daily Targum, and organized the first gay rights protest in New Jersey in 1976. After graduation, he attended New York University's (NYU) Graduate School of Film for one year. He moved to the Chelsea neighborhood of New York and worked as a sex worker, specifically as an S&M dominant, between 1978 and 1982.
In the late 1970s, Berkowitz met Dr. Joseph Sonnabend while seeking treatment at the Gay Men's Health Project clinic in New York City. In 1982, Berkowitz was diagnosed with AIDS. In laying out treatment options, Sonnabend shared his multifactorial theory of AIDS, which held that AIDS was caused by repeated exposure to sexually transmitted infections (STIs), in particular cytomegalovirus, and semen. This theory was in opposition to the more widely held theory at the time that a single, new infectious agent was the cause of AIDS. Berkowitz felt that gay men needed to know their risk of contracting AIDS and Sonnabend offered to introduce him to another of his patients with AIDS, Michael Callen, who was also interested in spreading this information to the gay community. Together, the three men are credited with creating the concept of safe sex. Berkowitz and Callen formed the support group Gay Men with AIDS and began writing about the multifactorial theory, AIDS, and safe sex. They wrote "We Know Who We Are", a warning to sexually active gay men with AIDS in New York, (published in the New York Native in 1982) and the first safe sex guide, How to Have Sex in an Epidemic: One Approach, published in 1983. They began making television appearances; speaking to support groups, legislators, and others; writing about AIDS; and were founding members of the People with AIDS Coalition.
Callen died in 1993 from AIDS-related complications. Sonnabend co-founded the AIDS Medical Foundation in 1983, and continued writing about AIDS issues and serving in private practice until his retirement in 2005. Berkowitz continued to write about AIDS, safe sex, and gay rights issues throughout the 1980s and into the 2000s. He returned to sex work in the late 1980s, promoting himself as a safe sex S&M dominant in Florida and New York. In 2003, he published his autobiography, Stayin' Alive, and in 2008 was the subject of Sex Positive, a documentary written and directed by Daryl Wein.
Custodial History
The collection was purchased by New York University (NYU) in November 2014 and the first accretion (2014.421) was transferred in December 2014 from the homes of two friends of Berkowitz's, Patrick Merla and Norma C. Connolly. Accretions 2015.421.001 and 2015.421.002 were transferred from Berkowitz's New York City apartment. Accretions 2015.421.003 and 2015.421.004 consist of seven of Berkowitz's email folders, totaling 4870 email messages. Accretion 2016.007 consists of one folder of Berkowitz's email, totaling 10583 email messages.
Items from this collection were used in the Fales Library's 2015 exhibition "Positive/Negative".
Related Materials
For more information regarding Joseph Sonnabend, see Joseph A. Sonnabend Papers, Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library. For more information regarding Michael Callen, see the Michael Callen Papers at the LGBT Community Center National History Archive.
Scope and Contents
The Richard Berkowitz Papers document the life and career of AIDS activist, writer, and safe-sex advocate Richard Berkowitz, particularly his writings on AIDS, safe sex, and gay rights issues; the documentary Sex Positive, about his life and work; his family; his education; his medical history; and his time as a sex worker. The papers date from 1944 to 2015, with the bulk being between 1982-2015. The bulk of the collection contains Berkowitz's work files, including drafts, notes, and published versions of his writings, including "We Know Who We Are", How to Have Sex in an Epidemic: One Approach, and Stayin' Alive; audio recordings of and correspondence with Michael Callen, Joseph Sonnabend, and others; video recordings of interviews with Callen, Larry Kramer, and others, and off-air recordings of AIDS-related programs; research files on different aspects of AIDS, safe sex, gay rights issues, and topics of interest to Berkowitz; and his website documenting his career, Safer Sex Positive. Material related to Berkowitz's undergraduate and graduate education includes his student films from Rutgers University and New York University. Material related to Berkowitz's medical history include his blood test results from the mid-1980s to the 2000s. Material related to Sex Positive includes correspondence with Daryl Wein, Sonnabend, and others; correspondence, programs, and other material related to film festivals Berkowitz attended in conjunction with the film; and newspaper and magazine clippings about the film. Material from Berkowitz's time as a sex worker includes correspondence with and photographs of clients; writings and photographs of clients used on his escort website, analorgasm.net; and some lists of clients and services he provided for them. His family records include a scrapbook compiled by his father, Milton Berkowitz, during his tour of duty with the United States Army in World War II; Milton Berkowitz's stag films; family home movies from the 1950s; and photographs of both parents, Berkowitz, his brothers, and their families.
Appraisal
Duplicates of periodicals and programs were deaccessioned, as were newspaper and magazine clippings, receipts, and ephemera not relevant to Berkowitz's interests or work. Floppy disks were deaccessioned after forensic imaging and analysis determined items contained no usable data.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Safe sex in AIDS prevention -- History; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); Homosexuality; Male prostitutes -- New York (State) -- New York; Gay authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; Pornographic films.; Amateur films; Audiocassettes.; Videocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Sonnabend, Joseph A.; Callen, Michael, 1955-1993
- Series I. Correspondence, 1973-2016, undated; 2009-2013; 0.1 Linear Feet in 3 folders.; 1.05 Gigabytes in 12,839 computer files.
  Scope and Content
  This series includes correspondence relating to Berkowitz's writings, post-AIDS crisis activism, interviews he conducted for an evaluation of National AIDS Fund grantees, gay rights, and personal correspondence with friends and family. Frequent correspondents include Jim Bredeson, Alex Fialho, David France, Sherri Lewis, Patrick Merla, Joseph Sonnabend, Sean Strub, Daryl Wein, Todd Wiggins, and Sharon Wood. The bulk of the correspondence is email with a small amount of paper correspondence.
  Arrangement
  The paper correspondence was arranged in loose chronological order by Berkowitz. He maintained folders in his email account for specific topics, as well as general correspondence.
  Original arrangement was maintained and is reflected in the following subseries:
  Subseries I.A. General, 1973-2016, undated
  Subseries I.B. Southern REACH (Regional Expansion of Access and Capacity to Address HIV/AIDS)/Gulf Coast HIV/AIDS Evaluations, 2009-2012
  Subseries I.C. Michael Callen Projects, 2012-2015
  Subseries I.D. Joseph Sonnabend, 2008-2015
  - Subseries I.A. General, 1973-2016, undated; 2008-2013; 0.1 Linear Feet in 3 folders.; 933.2 Megabytes in 12,082 messages in three email archives, and 19 computer files.
    This subseries includes correspondence relating to Berkowitz's speaking engagements and writings on AIDS and safe sex; requests to interview Berkowitz for documentaries, biographies, and museum and library exhibits; personal reflections from friends, family, and strangers upon seeing Sex Positive; personal experiences from individuals living with HIV/AIDS; and personal correspondence with friends and family. The bulk of the correspondence is email and includes attachments of word processing documents and photographs as well as voice messages from Abby Tallmer and others. Frequent correspondents include Berkowitz's brothers, sister-in-law, nephews, and niece; Michelle Cochrane; Norma C. Connolly; Greg Ellis; Alex Fialho; David France; Paula Frew; Kevin Kushel; Sherri Lewis; Ardele Lister; Patrick Merla; Spencer Schilly; Jeffrey Schwarz; Stephen Simon; Sean Strub; Abby Tallmer; Enrique Torre Molina; Daryl Wein; and Sharon Wood. There is a small amount of correspondence with Joseph Sonnabend.
    Conditions Governing Access
    The email in this subseries is closed until two years after the death of Richard Berkowitz.
    - Correspondence, 1973-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Email and correspondence, 1995-1997, 2008-2016; cuid41144
  - Subseries I.B. Southern REACH (Regional Expansion of Access and Capacity to Address HIV/AIDS)/Gulf Coast HIV/AIDS Evaluations, 2009-2012; 20.34 Megabytes in 276 computer files.
    This subseries contains email correspondence regarding telephone interviews conducted by Berkowitz on behalf of Paula Frew, an investigator at Emory University's Center for AIDS Research. He interviewed HIV/AIDS organizations in the southern United States that were grantees of a project funded by the National AIDS Fund to increase HIV/AIDS policy and advocacy outcomes in their regions. Correspondents include Frew and Carla Rotole, who transcribed the interviews.
    - Email, 2009-2012; cuid41145
  - Subseries I.C. Michael Callen Projects, 2012-2015; 2012; 45.97 Megabytes in 72 computer files.
    This subseries includes email correspondence regarding projects based on Michael Callen's life. The bulk of the correspondence is between Berkowitz and Jim Bredeson regarding the development of Even for One Night, a musical based on the life and work of Callen. The remaining correspondence is between Berkowitz and Martin Duberman regarding his book Hold Tight Gently: A Biography of Michael Callen, Essex Hemphill, and the Battlefield of AIDS and correspondence between Berkowitz and Richard Dworkin regarding Callen's life and legacy.
    - Email, 2012-2015; cuid41146
  - Subseries I.D. Joseph Sonnabend, 1997, 2008-2015; 55.58 Megabytes in 390 computer files.
    This subseries contains email correspondence between Berkowitz and Joseph Sonnabend regarding various topics, including day-to-day life, AIDS advocacy and policy work, the early history of AIDS, and the documentary Sex Positive. Discussion related to Sex Positive includes some reconciliation between Berkowitz, Sonnabend, and some of their opponents from the beginning of the AIDS crisis, including Larry Kramer and Rodger McFarlane, as well as continued friction with others, including Larry Mass. There is also correspondence between Berkowitz, Sean Strub, and Stephen Simon, some of which relates to Sonnabend, and voice messages from Sonnabend, mainly regarding day-to-day life.
    - Email and correspondence, 1997, 2008-2015; cuid41147
- Series II. Education, 1974-1980, undated; 0.5 Linear Feet in 6 legal-size folders and 4 oversize folders.; 3 audiocassettes; 32 film reels; 1 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
  This series documents Berkowitz's undergraduate and graduate education at Rutgers University and New York University (NYU), respectively. The series includes articles written by Berkowitz, student films he produced, financial records, and correspondence documenting Berkowitz's time at Rutgers and NYU.
  This series is arranged into the following subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Rutgers University, 1974-1977, undated
  Subseries II.B. New York University, 1977-1980, undated
  Material within the subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by type or topic of the material.
  - Subseries II.A. Rutgers University, 1974-1977, undated; 0.3 Linear Feet in 2 legal-size folders and 4 oversize folders.; 3 audiocassettes; 32 film reels; 1 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
    This subseries includes articles written by Berkowitz for Rutgers' campus newspaper, The Daily Targum; student films he produced; financial aid documents; and a poster for a film panel in which he participated.
    - Audio cassettes, 1975-1976 (Box 14, Cassette 421.0073-421.0076)
    - "The Changing Stereotypes of Women, Blacks, and Gays in Cinema"--poster, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Films, 1975-1977, undated; cuid41714
      - "La Brea" Outtakes -- Part I, March, 1976; cuid41715 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0001)
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        Duration: 3 minutes, 40 seconds.
      - "La Brea" Outtakes, January 13, 1977; cuid41716 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0002)
        Duration: 1 minute, 55 seconds.
      - "La Brea" Outtakes -- Rob, January 13, 1977; cuid41717 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0003)
        Duration: 2 minutes, 1 second
      - "La Brea" Outtakes -- Part II, March, 1976; cuid41718 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0004)
        Duration: 1 minute, 26 seconds
      - "The Cum-mercials" Outtakes -- Babes, Evans, Roy, Norma, May 17, 1976; cuid41719 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0006)
        Duration: 2 minutes, 16 seconds
      - "Cum-mercial", May, 1976; cuid41720 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0007)
        Duration: 6 minutes, 58 seconds
      - Pine Barren Doe Outtakes, undated; cuid41721 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0008)
        Duration: 5 minutes, 21 seconds
      - And Rose Titles, undated; cuid41722 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0009)
        Duration: 2 minutes, 38 seconds
      - For Sylvia -- Titles / Marilyn at Lib / Door Shot with Roy, October, 1975; cuid41723 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0010)
      - Marilyn [label illegible], Black Jill, undated; cuid41724 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0011)
        Duration: 1 minute, 39 seconds
      - And Rose, undated; cuid41725 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0012)
        Duration: 11 minutes, 51 seconds
      - Glory Hole Porno, undated; cuid41726 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0013)
        Duration: 10 minutes, 15 seconds
        Scope and Contents
        Content warning: This recording is sexually explicit.
      - Suburban Showdown, 1977; 421.0014 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0014)
        A student film directed by Richard Berkowitz.
        9 minutes 9 seconds, Black and White, Silent
      - Suburban Showdown [outtakes], 1977; 421.0015 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0015)
        Outtakes from Suburban Showdown, a student film directed by Richard Berkowitz.
        1 minute 6 seconds, Black and White, Silent
      - Untitled short film, undated; cuid41727 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0017)
        Duration: 6 minutes, 2 seconds
        The silent film depicts a woman with a painted face rising from bed, sitting at a table to eat a pie, and manipulating the pie with a fork.
      - The Oscar Wilde Memorial Bookshop, undated; cuid41728 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0018)
        Duration: 3 minutes, 20 seconds
        The silent film depicts scenes from picture books and comics at the Oscar Wilde Memorial Bookshop.
      - [Gay Rally], 1977; 421.0019 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0019)
        Contains footage from the 1977 Gay Pride Parade in New York City. Rollerena Fairy Godmother and Felipe Rose of The Village People make brief appearances.
        3 minutes, Color, Silent
      - [Home movie], 1975; 421.0020 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0020)
        Contains Double-exposed footage of a family vacationing near a lake.
        3 minutes 21 seconds, Color, Silent
      - Rutgers Film Assignment, June, 1974; cuid41729 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0021)
        Duration: 3 minutes, 21 seconds
      - Suicide Jump, March, 1974; cuid41730 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0022)
        Duration: 2 minutes, 3 seconds
        Content warning: This recording includes explicit sexual imagery.
      - Library scenes, undated; cuid41731 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0023)
        Duration: 1 minute, 45 seconds
      - Rain / Single frame / New Hpe, May-June, 1974; cuid41732 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0024)
      - Expo 67, Montreal, undated; cuid41733 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0026)
        Duration: 3 minutes, 32 seconds
      - Untitled short film, undated; cuid41734 (Box 17, Super 8mm film reel 421.0027)
        Duration: 2 minutes, 58 seconds
        The silent film depicts a woman with a painted face and a man jumping from a rooftop.
      - Lending close-up / Titles, undated; cuid41735 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0028)
        Duration: 1 minute, 7 seconds
      - "X-orcist" -- Waste credits, shots at 1383 Omara Dr., undated; cuid41736 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0029)
        Duration: 2 minutes, 19 seconds
      - Library scenes, undated; cuid41737 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0030)
        Duration: 1 minute, 55 seconds
      - Untitled short film, April, 1974; cuid41738 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0031)
        Duration: 2 minute, 53 seconds
        The film depicts a woman with a painted face stirring a pie with a fork. The end of the film has a short library scene.
      - Left-over film from porno, undated; cuid41739 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0032)
        Duration: 3 minutes, 42 seconds
      - At Seventeen, 1974-1979; 421.0033 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0033)
        Contains footage of street scenes and scenery taken in the areas around Rutgers University.
        2 minutes 30 seconds, Color, Silent
      - Video (Box 16, Video 421.0209)
    - Movie notes, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - The Daily Targum, 1974-1977, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Radio and voice message clips, cuid43949 (Box 17, Quarter inch audio reel 421.0016)
      This recording includes clips of music interspersed with a voice message for Berkowitz.
      Duration: 30 minutes; Preservation Note: Very poor audio quality.
  - Subseries II.B. New York University, 1977-1980, undated; 0.2 Linear Feet in 6 folders.; 4 film reels; 1 audiocassette
    This subseries contains Berkowitz's notes, script, and films for his student film, Selling It; report cards; resumes; class notes; and correspondence with NYU administrators.
    - Correspondence, 1977-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)